<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Dee's Blog</title><description>Thoughts, stories and ideas worth sharing.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/</link><image><url>http://localhost:2369/favicon.png</url><title>Dee's Blog</title><link>http://localhost:2369/</link></image><generator>Ghost 3.13</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 03:32:54 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2369/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Team CircuitBreakers from Sri Lanka wins the second Runner Up in the first-ever virtual International Micromouse Challenge - Techfest, 2020 🥉</title><description>Sri Lanka secures an International Award in robotics after a long time. This article states the importance of victories like this for Sri Lankan robotics enthusiasts.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/team-circuitbreakers-from-sri-lanka-wins-the-second-runner-up-in-the-first-ever-virtual-international-micromouse-challenge-techfest-2020/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5fed2e653273d28675e56f4e</guid><category>Robotics</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 02:11:39 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/12/techfest-2020-team.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/12/techfest-2020-team.png" alt="Team CircuitBreakers from Sri Lanka wins the second Runner Up in the first-ever virtual International Micromouse Challenge - Techfest, 2020 🥉"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone, it's the end of the year 2020 and our team &amp;quot;CircuitBreakers&amp;quot; has been able to secure the Second Runner Up award in the International Micromouse Challenge organised along with Techfest 2020 (&lt;a href="https://techfest.org"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;); Asia's largest Science and Technology Festival in its 24th edition. The competition successfully concluded on 26th of December, 2020 with more than 300 registrations. This is the first time after 11 years our mother nation was able to secure an award after Mr. Salinda and his team won the championship (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XUnKCdMu6_0"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;) in 2009. I thought of writing an article after many requests from our friends and mentors. Therefore, this article is written in the goodwill of sharing our journey and experience so far and also to raise awareness of the importance of this milestone in the Sri Lankan Robotics arena.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h3 id="whatisanimcinternationalmicromousechallenge"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is an IMC (International Micromouse Challenge)?&lt;/strong&gt; 💭&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who don't know yet of micromouse competitions I will briefly tell you a bit about that. In our childhood we all have come across the small challenge of the &amp;quot;rat and the carrot&amp;quot; challenge where we have to guide the rat to the carrot by tracing the path with a pencil. In the same analogy, here the goal is to design, program and develop a robot mouse who can start at a corner of the wall maze and go to the center while solving the maze in the least amount of time. The mouse can explore the maze in the given time and can have several runs to the center and return back. The minimum run time from start to the center is used to determine the winner. As the common practise there are two runs called the “search run” and the “fast run” where in the search run the micromouse tries to find its way to its center using the common &amp;quot;flood fill&amp;quot; algorithm (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flood_fill"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;) while saving the maze wall configuration in its memory. After the shortest path is found, the mouse executes the fast run from the available wall data of the maze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Micromouse Competitions can be considered as another kind of sport where there's no age gap to participate as well as there's no limit of knowledge to learn. The IEEE Micromouse standard (&lt;a href="https://ewh.ieee.org/sb/columbus/devry/sacFiles/MicromouseRules.pdf"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;) maze consist of 16x16 cells and the current world record is 3.921 seconds which is held by Ng Beng Kia. There are several International Micromouse Challenges/ Competitions (IMC) spread across the world. Some popular competitions among these are All Japan Micromouse Competition (&lt;a href="http://www.ntf.or.jp/mouse/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;), Taiwan Micromouse Intelligent Robot Contest (&lt;a href="http://robot.lhu.edu.tw/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;), APEC MicroMouse Contest (&lt;a href="http://www.apec-conf.org/conference/participating-in-micromouse/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;) and Techfest IMC (&lt;a href="https://techfest.org/competitions/micromouse"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). Furthermore there are many nation wide competitions in the USA, UK, Singapore and many more countries. More information can be found by visiting these two popular websites. (&lt;a href="http://www.micromouseonline.com"&gt;Micromouse Online&lt;/a&gt;  and &lt;a href="http://micromouseusa.com"&gt;Micromouse USA&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/12/1600px-Micromouse_maze.jpg" alt="Team CircuitBreakers from Sri Lanka wins the second Runner Up in the first-ever virtual International Micromouse Challenge - Techfest, 2020 🥉"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h3 id="whybuildamicromouse"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why build a micromouse?&lt;/strong&gt; 🛠&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a broad topic that suits a separate article but, I will explain for the enthusiastic readers who read up to hear for your knowledge. Micromouse competitions fall under robotics competitions therefore indeed a person needs to have thorough knowledge in electronics, programming and mechanics to build one. But the robot is small enough even for a kid to start building compared to a complex robot arm. The hardware can go from using a cheap ultrasonic sensor to high resolution IR sensor and from using a cheap DC motor to a high resolution premium encoder Faulhaber motor (&lt;a href="https://www.faulhaber.com/en/products/dc-motors/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). Applying the same in the software aspect, one can program using the simple Arduino platform or using the complex industrial platforms. The Fastrun algorithms can be simulated using programming platforms and can be researched up to a PhD study. Therefore building a micromouse can benefit whether you are a kid stepping into robotics or whether you are an expert in the field of robotics. Here is a photo of previous micromouse robot we have build called &amp;quot;Wega Batta v2.0&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/12/Wega-Batta.JPG" alt="Team CircuitBreakers from Sri Lanka wins the second Runner Up in the first-ever virtual International Micromouse Challenge - Techfest, 2020 🥉"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h3 id="covidpandemicandvirtualcompetitionspace"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Covid Pandemic and Virtual Competition Space&lt;/strong&gt; 😷&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of Covid pandemic, a major impact happened to the International robotics competition space. As a result of that many online robotics platforms have emerged to fill the gap of learning robotics effectively. I will write a separate article soon on learning robotics effectively in the midst of covid. But still, no proper solution is there to hold the competitions online as it's nearly impossible to do robotics without physical hardware. But for robots that don't require much hardware complexity can be simulated through softwares like Robot Operating System (ROS) and Webots platforms which are both open-source. The first competition held in Sri Lanka virtually is the IESL Robogames 2020 competition organised by the IESL IT &amp;amp; Communication Engineering Sectional Committee in collaboration with University of Moratuwa Computer Science Engineering department. I'm really happy that our juniors representing &amp;quot;CircuitBreakers Robotics&amp;quot; won the championship in this competition as well. Here they have used the “Webots” platform to conduct the competition. In Techfest 2020 IMC; being one of the first competitions to conduct online, they have used ROS to conduct the competition. Let's have a look on how the competition is conducted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h3 id="howcompetitionwasheld"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Competition was held?&lt;/strong&gt; 🏁&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The teams were given a sample maze created in the Gazebo application in ROS Melodic environment with a sample robot URDF (Unified Robotic Description Format) configured. Then the teams are allowed to program either in C++ or Python2 as they preferred. At the first round teams had to submit a video demonstrating their run in the sample maze given. Based on that teams were shortlisted to participate in the finals. Each team received a 20 mins time slot to compete where their submitted code is run in the final maze. The simulation time was used to determine the final scores with addition of negative marks for any collisions with the maze walls. The winners were announced after all the teams have competed and the judges have finalised their decision. Here you can find our demostration video we have submitted for the first round. (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xJbJIcLlkn0&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h3 id="whyisthisawardgreatforsrilankans"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is this award great for Sri Lankans?&lt;/strong&gt; 🇱🇰&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our seniors from the Electronic and Telecommunications department have participated in the International Robotics Competition arena previously in competitions like Robocon 2019, IRC (International Robotics Challenge) by IIT Bombay, IMC 2009 by IIT Bombay and many more. But due to high competition our teams had to work hard to achieve awards and not in every time we have been able to secure one. After being champions in IMC 2009 in Techfest 2009, it's after 11 years our team has won the 2nd Runner Up award which marks a milestone in Sri Lankan Robotics history. We are hoping this achievement will encourage our young budding robotics enthusiasts to follow our footsteps to bring greater victories to our motherland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h3 id="ourapproachtomicromouseandros"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our approach to Micromouse and ROS&lt;/strong&gt; 👨🏻‍💻&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have used python2 as the programming language to program the robot. Here we first simulated the flood-fill algorithm while at the same time tested the fundamental robot functions like turning left, right and moving a single cell while following walls. After that we integrated the core code with the traversing algorithm together to work seamlessly. Here we have used version control systems like Git to work online collaboratively. We have used our own variance of flood fill algorithm and a curve turn algorithm. The biggest challenge we have found is the high performance requirement that was needed to simulate the robot. To solve that we had to find a high performance laptop and install Ubuntu operating system separately rather than running on a virtual machine. Also we have tweaked the URDF of the robot to suit our requirements of fast turning and stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/12/ros-maze.png" alt="Team CircuitBreakers from Sri Lanka wins the second Runner Up in the first-ever virtual International Micromouse Challenge - Techfest, 2020 🥉"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h3 id="ourteam"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Our Team&lt;/strong&gt; ❤️&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I thought it would be great to have a little note about our team and qualifications that enabled us to achieve this award. Of course dedication, patience and enthusiasm is a must to win robot competitions. Being all team members from the Electronic and Telecommunications Engineering undergraduates at University of Moratuwa we have a fundamental knowledge in Electronics and Programming. Being the leader of the team, I had two previous experiences in building micromouse robots which was named &amp;quot;Wega Batta&amp;quot; (&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SLhiuWBg2WA"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;) and currently I’m working as a visiting researcher (student) at University of Sydney, Faculty of Engineering. Next &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dilanka-laknath-02b739181/"&gt;Dilanka&lt;/a&gt; had experience in building a micromouse and also he’s continuing his internship in Zone24x7 which is a well known robotics company in Sri Lanka. &lt;a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/shalutharajapakshe"&gt;Shalutha&lt;/a&gt; also built a micromouse himself previously and currently doing his internship at CSIRO Data61 Robotics and Autonomous Systems Group, Australia. At last but not least, &lt;a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/punsaramahawela"&gt;Punsara&lt;/a&gt; studies in his second year and he is very passionate about robotics and has participated in many competitions since his school time. Also he was the leader of the team which won the IESL Robogames 2020 competition which is the first virtual robotics competition in Sri Lanka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h3 id="whatsnext"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's next?&lt;/strong&gt; 🤩&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We as &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/CircuitBreakersRobotics"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CircuitBreakers Robotics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are working towards empowering the robotics education in Sri Lanka with our ever-learning knowledge and experience. We are envisioned to make available free robotics online resources for anyone to learn robotics which is not currently available for Sri Lankan students. We are also looking forward to participating in more International Robotics Competitions in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we are more than happy to receive your suggestions and comments on this article for us to improve in the future. Thank you and stay tuned for more updates in the future. Happy time building robots! 🤖🛠&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hate having to take multiple books with you every time? Join the PaperlessMovement 📝</title><description>Did you know that digitalizing your workflow can increase your productivity by 60%? In this article, I would like to share my experience with digital notetaking.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/hate-having-to-take-different-books-to-your-classes-join-the-paperlessmovement/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5fc31b6fffddac1493f8c4ec</guid><category>Lifestyle</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 04:52:48 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/11/PaperlessMovement-Thumbnail.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/11/PaperlessMovement-Thumbnail.png" alt="Hate having to take multiple books with you every time? Join the PaperlessMovement 📝"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I will be sharing something interesting that I have found 1.5 years ago. It might be something common to you as well. I’m a person who likes to carry as less things as possible to do some task and always trying to be efficient in terms of what I do. I hated to carry multiple books in my school days but as we can’t write everything in one book which makes everything messy, I had to carry multiple books every time with me to school and even to the university later on. My whole life changed when my sister who is a PhD candidate in Missouri, USA sent me an Apple iPad Pro 2019 11-inch model with Apple Pencil 2. Here in this short article, I would like to share my whole story with my iPad so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="whyihatemanagingmultiplebooks"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why I hate managing multiple books?&lt;/strong&gt; 😫&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several reasons why I hate managing multiple books. Among them I will share with you the top 3 reasons. The first one is when I have to study for the exams, I can’t quickly refer to the needed pages specially when I have to cross refer some parts from different books. The second reason would be in order to study I always had to have the correct book with me. Sometimes I forget to carry the needed book with me only realizing about it after I have come to the university from the boarding. The third reason would be that most of my friends including me study in the university library most of the time where bags are not allowed so that we have to carry the books, pencils and other stationaries with us when going to the library from the department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="digitalnotetakingpaperlessmovement"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital Notetaking - PaperlessMovement&lt;/strong&gt; 📝&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently figured out there is this interesting movement called the PaperlessMovement which was founded by Dr. Thomas Roedl, aka &amp;quot;Tom Solid&amp;quot; who is a youtuber and a blogger. He states that as in the modern world everything is transforming into a digital workflow therefore by moving analog notetaking which is writing on books to digital notetaking can result in the productivity increase in 60%. If you want to know more information about the movement, please go and check out his official website. (&lt;a href="https://www.paperlessmovement.com"&gt;https://www.paperlessmovement.com&lt;/a&gt;) His main intention is not about the exact digital notetaking device that you use but more about the process of digitalizing your workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="mystory"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My story&lt;/strong&gt; 👨🏻‍💻&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me Apple iPad has given me a huge bump in my productivity as all the semester notes and everything I had in my one thin beautiful device where I can carry anywhere. If someone is interested in what exactly I bought I have added the list of products I bought together here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The stuff I bought are as follows,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iPad Pro 2019 11 inch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple pencil gen 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zugu Muse case for iPad pro 11 - &lt;a href="https://www.zugucase.com/the-muse-case-2018-ipad-pro-11-old-model/"&gt;https://www.zugucase.com/the-muse-case-2018-ipad-pro-11-old-model/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matte screen protector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/11/ipad-photo.jpg" alt="Hate having to take multiple books with you every time? Join the PaperlessMovement 📝"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here the biggest experience shift came from applying a &lt;strong&gt;matte screen protector&lt;/strong&gt; which brought the same sound and feeling as writing on a normal piece of paper. Also the new Apple Pencil could be charged wirelessly and the latency is so low that is undetectable from the naked eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purchasing a digital notetaking device is just the first step of the journey. Then you need to find proper applications that will help you to be more productive. Here are the most used apps that helped me along the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="mytop10favouriteapps"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My top 10 favourite Apps&lt;/strong&gt; 🤩&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goodnotes 5&lt;/strong&gt;– Even though this is a paid app in the Appstore, this app has so many features that helps to take notes, keep other lecture materials and past papers at a single place. The one-time payment has been an investment in myself in this whole journey. A similar productive app would be “Notability”. Here are some of the snapshots on how I used this in my academic work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/11/goodnotes-snaps.jpg" alt="Hate having to take multiple books with you every time? Join the PaperlessMovement 📝"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Microsoft Onedrive&lt;/strong&gt; – As the university account grants us 1 TB of online data storage, all my files are stored in OneDrive including videos and everything. I use this app a lot for cloud file sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Udemy, Coursera apps&lt;/strong&gt; – iPad brought me a whole new experience in doing online courses as the big display and convenient build made me enjoy learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google calender&lt;/strong&gt; – This is a very good app to organize your meetings with your friends and other work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apple reminder app&lt;/strong&gt; – To be more productive it’s a must to organize your daily tasks and finishing them withing the day. The native apple reminder app is the app I found the best to manage my tasks as it seamlessly integrated with my iPhone and Macbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apple notes&lt;/strong&gt; – I keep short notes and quick notes which are not related to academic work in this app mainly about the startup work, voluntary work and personal notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PDF Expert&lt;/strong&gt; – This is another free app to manage your PDFs and add signatures. I use this app a lot in my startup work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Meet and Zoom&lt;/strong&gt; – These two apps are mainly used for online meeting purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vectornator&lt;/strong&gt; – This is an amazing little app which allows you to draw vectors like Illustrator for PCs. Even though I’m not good as an artist I have used this app to create some designs and logos whenever I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/11/vectornator-snaps.jpg" alt="Hate having to take multiple books with you every time? Join the PaperlessMovement 📝"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="10"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yoink&lt;/strong&gt; - This app can be used to store images, PDFs, other text which acts as a universal clipboard. We can add content to this from any app and later use drag and drop function to add the content to any other app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more than 100 applications in my device and above are the most frequently used apps I have figured out to be the most productive. Feel free to share your favorite apps below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="amisatisfied"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Am I satisfied?&lt;/strong&gt; 😌&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After using the device nearly for 2 years, even now I enjoy picking it up to take some quick notes whenever I need. But as the nature of everything there are pros and cons of everything. If you are technologically wise, you can definitely benefit from digitalizing your workflow. But be aware of side effects such as eye strain and digital dementia due to over usage of digital devices. Sometimes, this might not work for you as it worked for me in my workflow. My main intention was to raise awareness about the PaperlessMovement and you also can get benefited from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="istillpreferprintedbooks"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I still prefer printed books!&lt;/strong&gt; 📖❤️&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I have found that occasionally I really enjoy writing something down on personal diaries specially about my personal goals and personal notes. Also, I really like paperback books on personal stories and self-help books. Honestly, I prefer printed books over eBooks as the the feel and the nourishing smell can only be taken by a printed book. I will keep this eBooks vs printed books argument for a future article ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading this up to the very end. Please add your comments and valuable suggestions to improve my articles in the future. I hope you will have gained some valuable information on digital notetaking from my own journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Why consider learning Robotics in 2021? 🤖</title><description>Robotics has turned out to be a promising field with the current trend in the world. This article is written with the intention of raising awareness about why it's important to all of us even you are student, parent or etc.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/why-consider-learning-robotics-in-2021/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5f9e824bc1dc7d3a1230779c</guid><category>Robotics</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 10:40:08 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/11/Why-learn-robotics-2.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/11/Why-learn-robotics-2.png" alt="Why consider learning Robotics in 2021? 🤖"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hello Everyone, I thought of writing a small article to raise awareness of the importance of robotics education in this difficult times where most of you might be working or studying from home or you might be going to school and your studies might have been interrupted by now. The year 2020 has turned out to be a year like never before where we had to change and adapt everything that we have been used to do in the past. So, without further a due, Let’s dive into the field of robotics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of us got to know about the concepts of a robot from the famous “Transformers” movie. We know how powerful the “Optimus Prime” is. We all love the “Bumblebee”. Coming over to my favorite the robot “Wall-E” which is helping the world to recycle the waste. But when it comes to the real-world robotics it might be quite different. As Wikipedia defines,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Robotics involves design, construction, operation, and use of robots. Robotics develops machines that can substitute for humans and replicate human actions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, robots are designed to help humans and to automate repetitive human tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robotics and automation is one of the emerging fields which has a lot of potential in the future. With the growing uncertainty of things in the world, people have realized the value of automation and utilizing the human resources in the most efficient way. Therefore, learning about robotics is a wonderful investment for the future. I think now we are in the same page about the importance of robotics education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most common question that you might think right now would be whether robotics is for me or will this article would help me? This article can be helpful for you even if you are parent who is looking for what suits the best for your child or if you are an university student who is trying to find your passion or even if you are still pursuing your school studies who wants to learn something new outside from the school curriculum. Also, this article can help investors or even the government in identifying the importance of robotics education for the young generation who will lead our mother nation for the next technology revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Getting back to the childhood we know how we used to play with sand, smell the fresh air, see the horizon and be amazed by the beauty of nature, make clay castles and etc. Kids like to play with tangible things, things that they can touch, feel and react. But when we came to school we had to read, write and face exams. We used far more less practical experience in the things we learned. Exams defined our results not the applications. But as many research studies have found that the most effective learning comes through engaging all the senses in the learning process starting from watching, listening, writing, teaching and most importantly applying it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most amazing fact is that learning robotics stimulate all of these senses in order to learn effectively while providing kids something tangible to work with. This learning procedure is systemized as “STEAM” education which is the new normal of education that is to use Science and Technology interpreted through Engineering and Arts based on Mathematics. That's why Robotics is proven to be one of the best ways to teach “STEAM” education-based learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Robotics is a multi-disciplinary field which combines the expertise in the field of Electronics, Computer Science and Mechanics. Therefore, it’s not just about a single field of interest but more about how different people from different disciplines get together and work for a common goal. This particular quality has been able to develop teamwork and leadership skills in individuals who learn robotics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/11/kids-creating-robots.jpg" alt="Why consider learning Robotics in 2021? 🤖"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of more personal benefits in learning robotics as well. Even in Sri Lanka, there are plenty of robotics competitions organized by many Universities which you can participate in school, undergraduate and open categories. Participating in these competitions will help you to build several life skills such as working hard, dedication, commitment and also to accept failures. Sometimes a small mistake can lead to lose in the final round in a competition which might be frustrating for a moment but later you learn the lesson. An interesting fact is that robotics competitions can also be seen as a new kind of sport. Also, students can gain more international exposure by participate in international robotics competitions as well. As mentioned at the beginning of the article, robots are used to automate human tasks which is to solve practical problems. Therefore, by learning robotics students can practice solving real world problems with their infinite creativity and imagination that they already poses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moving on to the future it’s pretty sure that the world will move towards to cut down labour intensive tasks and assign them to robots. Human resources will be used for far more valuable decision making and innovative things. Most of the labour-intensive jobs might get replaced by robots. There will be millions of new job opportunities because of this technology change. But still, no robot has been developed to outperform the thinking ability of humans. Therefore, there are always opportunities for those who are creative and innovative. Also, a funny fact is that, if you are the one who develops robots you won’t be replaced at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;I know now you are really enthusiastic to learn or share this with someone you love. There are cutting-edge technologies involved in the field of robotics. Earlier, robots are used in manufacturing under heavy safety measures in operating areas. But, the new era of robotics is to develop robots that can work in human centered environments. Legged robots, robot hands and many more are developed to look like humans and work like humans to be more friendly to us. Most of the major countries  like China, USA, Switzerland and Japan are pioneers in robotics at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming to the end of the article, I would like to humbly share what we do for the betterment of robotics education in Sri Lanka. We as “CircuitBreakers Robotics”; a startup initiated by robotics enthusiasts who are currently undergraduates of University of Moratuwa we have a vision to empower robotics education in Sri Lankan by providing related services and free education. We believe that robotics education should be available for every single person in Sri Lanka as we had the privilege of public education from the school to the university. The problem is that robotics is not directly included in our school curriculum and the knowledge is not out there with proper quality. We are on our way to create the first ever robotics platform for Sri Lankans and recently, we have launched our facebook community called “&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/circuitbreakersrobotics/"&gt;CircuitBreakers Robotics Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;” where any individual can ask their questions and get answers from the experts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I invite all the readers to join with us to help us through this great journey. Thank you! Happy time building robots ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Why do you need mentoring? - Life with ScholarX #1 🎓</title><description>In this article I express my journey so far with ScholarX program by SEF which highlights the importance of mentoring for both the mentor and the mentee.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/why-do-you-need-mentoring/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5efc7c855334a413ea409f79</guid><category>Lifestyle</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 12:18:37 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/07/ScholarX1_Cover.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="whatismentoring"&gt;What is mentoring?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/07/ScholarX1_Cover.png" alt="Why do you need mentoring? - Life with ScholarX #1 🎓"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mentorship is a relationship in which a more experienced or more knowledgeable person helps to guide a less experienced or less knowledgeable person. The mentor may be older or younger than the person being mentored (the mentee), but they must have a certain area of expertise. It’s always the volunteering of both sides which strengthen this bond. Some person might be a mentor to someone and also being a mentee of someone at the same time. A person may not be restricted to only have a single mentor throughout his/her life. The first mentors we meet is our own parents. From there onwards, we meet various mentors to guide us through the journey of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="whymentoringisimportant"&gt;Why mentoring is important?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mentoring allows a person to boost his/her career. Mentoring can be seen as a shortcut to success. Why should we fall on the same pit which someone else has fallen before and in the same debate, why shouldn’t we apply the path to success which someone else has already been succeeded. In other hand, being a good mentor to a mentee has benefits too. It helps someone to develop the skill of influencing, motivating and out of all, the most important which is the happiness by helping out someone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a message by &lt;strong&gt;Winston Churchill&lt;/strong&gt; to all the great mentors out there who are helping others to succeed,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We make a living by what we get, we make a life by what we give”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="scholarxprogrambysustainableeducationfoundationsef"&gt;ScholarX program by Sustainable Education Foundation (SEF)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start off, this is what the SEF Global tells about its mentoring program in a nutshell,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“ScholarX is an exclusive 6-month program aimed at providing mentoring support to a selected pool of high Potential undergraduate students based in Sri Lanka ideally by a Sri Lankan expat currently engaged with one of the world’s top universities or Fortune 500 companies. It’s our free premium mentoring platform by Sri Lankans for Sri Lankans working towards creating a culture of knowledge and expertise sharing without the limitation of geographical borders.” – SEF Global&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ScholarX program helps undergraduates in Sri Lanka to provide them with free premium mentorship from the successful people in the world of academics and business. The ScholarX 2019 program was a huge success which inspired me to apply for the this year program. This time in ScholarX 2020, there was a great collection of mentors covering almost all the areas considering every undergraduate. An interview process is done to filter out applicants and to match the mentors with the mentees. For more information about the ScholarX program visit, &lt;a href="https://sefglobal.org/scholarx/2020/"&gt;https://sefglobal.org/scholarx/2020/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="whyineededmentoring"&gt;Why I needed mentoring&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the readers who are reading my articles for the first time, I would like to say a bit about me. I’m a passionate individual who likes to face new challenges, adapt to new opportunities and more over likes to challenge myself out from my comfort zone. I have a been a very studios person since my childhood focusing more on academics which resulted in achieving good results in A/L exams as well as my current Electronics and Telecommunication engineering degree at University of Moratuwa. I’m passionate more into robotics and computer algorithms. These days I’m trying myself out in the vast world of entrepreneurship in the journey of building the dream team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I always like to find new opportunities, I always needed help from the people who can provide guidance and support in different areas of life; academics, career, lifestyle, personal growth and etc. These guidance not only help to avoid the roadblocks in life but also to discover new areas hidden unseen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="mymentor"&gt;My Mentor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I love to learn about computer algorithms and to participate in competitive programming competitions my first choice was Mr. Chethiya Abeysinghe who is currently a software engineer at Google. I would like to really express my gratitude towards ScholarX program for the opportunity to get connected with him. He’s also an alumina of our own department who has excelled in computer algorithms field. His team won the iEEEXtreme world championship once. Also, he has won several awards at International Olympiad in Informatics (IOI). He has done several webinars on programming and algorithms along with Sustainable Education Foundation (SEF Global). Here is our amazing mentoring group mentored by Mr.Chethiya Abeysinghe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/07/mentor_group_scholarx.JPG" alt="Why do you need mentoring? - Life with ScholarX #1 🎓"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="thejourneysofar"&gt;The journey so far...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first challenge was to setup a time for the group mentoring sessions which we have scheduled at 5 am weekly at a weekend day. Waking up in the morning always been a challenge to me. I never go to university morning lectures on time, but I didn’t miss a single mentoring session till now which really helped to move one step further in time management. The sessions are always friendly and welcoming.  Here, I learned the importance of computer algorithms, coding interviews and knowledge about technology which I’m planning to cover in the upcoming articles in this series of articles about the ScholarX program. It’s almost two months passed in the 6-month period. Hope to learn more and unlock new areas in life with the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings an end to this articles. Please add any comments or suggestions to improve my articles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for more articles like this in the future!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Read this before using lipo batteries again 🔋</title><description>Li-Po batteries are popular among the robotics community. In this article, I'm sharing my experience and knowledge I have learned of using Li-Po batteries.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/read-this-before-using-lipo-batteries-again/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5edf0cab328a04272e7c1878</guid><category>Robotics</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 05:02:30 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/06/Lipo-batteries-cover-1.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/06/Lipo-batteries-cover-1.jpg" alt="Read this before using lipo batteries again 🔋"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When building robots, drones and electronic products supplying power is a critical factor. Batteries are used to supply power to the components where the product is required to be mobile. Lithium-Polymer (Li-Po) batteries are commonly used as a power source for many drones, mobile robots, remote control cars and other electronics products. In this article, I would like to mention some of the facts I have learned through my experience and the things I have learned from the internet about using Li-Po batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Li-po batteries are usually high-current batteries which should be handled with care. Before dive deep into this, let’s compare these li-po batteries to lithium-ion batteries that are commonly found in our mobile phones and many consumer electronic products.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="comparisonoflipobatteriestoliionbatteries"&gt;Comparison of li-po batteries to li-ion batteries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/06/Comparison_lipo_liion.png" class="kg-image" alt="Read this before using lipo batteries again 🔋"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;comparison of li-ion and li-po batteries&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the comparison above it can be seen why lithium ion batteries are more popular for usage in mobile phones and devices that require less power and li-po batteries for the drones and RC cars which require higher current.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="typesoflipobatteries"&gt;Types of lipo batteries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Li-po batteries come in various sizes, capacities, voltages and etc. But it can be scene that a single cell voltage of these batteries is the same. To get higher voltages batteries are connected in series. Let’s dive into the numbers and letters that can be seen in the label of the li-po battery packs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/06/standard_lipo_battery.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Read this before using lipo batteries again 🔋"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Li-Po Battery with labels&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h3 id="1voltagecellcount"&gt;1. Voltage / cell count&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The battery pack consists of several batteries connected in series and parallel which indicated in the battery wrapping. The nominal voltage of a single cell is &lt;strong&gt;3.7V&lt;/strong&gt; which is the voltage that the battery supplies when its being discharged halfway. When the battery is fully charged it will give around &lt;strong&gt;4.2V&lt;/strong&gt; and when it’s adviced not to drain a single cell more than 3V. Li-Po battery packs come in different voltages such as 3.7V, 7.4V, 11.V and so on which are integer multiplies of the nominal voltage of a single cell battery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, the “3S” indicated in the battery tells that the battery pack has 3 single cells connected in series. If some pack has “2S2P”, it indicates that the battery pack has 2 single cells connected in series first and two of these are connected parallelly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;personal choice&lt;/strong&gt; for my robotics applications and electronic projects are the &lt;strong&gt;2S 7.4V&lt;/strong&gt; battery packs as they can be regulated down to get 5V/3V3 for microcontrollers and sensors or stepped up to get 12V for the motor applications. If we use 3S 11.V battery pack for 12V application, you might have to use a step up/ step down regulator to remove the effect which is caused by when the battery is fully charged it will have 12.6V and when it drains it drops down below 12V.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h3 id="2capacity"&gt;2. Capacity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water tanks store water where water can be taken out when needed for applications. Batteries are similar to water tanks, but they store energy rather than water. The capacity of the battery measures how much energy can be stored in a battery. Normally the capacity is given in &amp;quot;mAh&amp;quot; in the label of the battery. The capacity value comes in handy to measure how long the battery can supply the required power to the circuit when a given amount of current is drawn from the circuit. For an example, the battery given above has 2200mAh and if the circuit draws 100mA the circuit can be powered for,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2200mAh/100mA = 44hours&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h3 id="3dischargerating"&gt;3. Discharge rating&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might have wander about the huge number with the suffix “C” letter written on the label of the battery pack. This is called the “C” rating of the battery pack which is a widely used term to calculate the maximum discharging current that can be delivered without harming the battery. You cannot find the max current by only knowing the “C” rating alone. You also need the capacity of the battery for this too. You can just simply multiply the “C” rating with the capacity in Ah and you will get the max current in Amperes. For the above battery the max current for discharging is,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.2Ahx20 = 22Amperes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h3 id="4internalresistance"&gt;4. Internal resistance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This value is something which is not indicated in the label of the battery pack. It has a reason for that which is the internal resistance value varies with the aging of the battery and the battery voltage. For a healthy battery pack this value can be several ohms but for a damaged battery this can be a large value which reduces the terminal voltage of the battery when delivering to a load.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="lipobatteryconnectors"&gt;Li-Po battery connectors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Li-po battery packs usually have 2 connectors for discharging and charging separately. Discharging socked only consists of 2 pins (positive and negative) while the charging socket consisting of numbering pins equal to number of cells + 1 usually. There are various connectors used for these sockets. Some common ones are,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deans Connector&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/06/deans-t-plug.jpg" alt="Read this before using lipo batteries again 🔋"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XT-60 Connector&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/06/XT60.jpg" alt="Read this before using lipo batteries again 🔋"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JST-XH Connector&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/06/JST-HS254-3.jpg" alt="Read this before using lipo batteries again 🔋"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can change the connectors when we need to extent the length of the wires. When changing the connector, we have to cut the wires of the discharging connector. Here we have to cut the ground wire first and then the positive wire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never cut both wires at the same time as the plier will short the terminals of the battery.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/06/terminal_cutting.jpg" alt="Read this before using lipo batteries again 🔋"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also keep in mind not to swap the two terminals (use correct polarity) when connecting the socket to the electronic product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="charginglipobatteries"&gt;Charging Li-Po batteries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even though li-po batteries are less explosive than li-ion batteries, they should be handled with care. Li-po batteries have a smaller number of charging cycles compared to li-ion. Therefore, proper charging should be done to maintain the batteries in good health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="1selectingacharger"&gt;1. Selecting a charger&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/06/Lipo-charger-cheap.jpg" alt="Read this before using lipo batteries again 🔋"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You all might have seen the cheap conventional charger which are readily available in electronic shops shown in the picture. These chargers don’t charge all the cells of the battery to the same level which degrades the battery a lot. This also causes to increase the internal resistance of a single cell in the long run which will totally destroy that cell. There are good balance chargers which monitor the current to each individual cell and charges in &lt;strong&gt;constant current/ constant voltage (CC/ CD)&lt;/strong&gt; charging method which maintains the health of the battery. These chargers even can identify whether the battery is connected correctly. One of the chargers I am using currently is shown below. These can be ordered online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/06/lipo_balance_charger.jpg" alt="Read this before using lipo batteries again 🔋"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One of the factors to keep in mind is that to never leave batteries charging unattended.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The max charging rate of the battery is indicated as the charging &amp;quot;C&amp;quot; rating. For the above battery it's &amp;quot;2C&amp;quot; which means that the maximum charging current is,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.2Ah x 2 = 4.2Amperes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id="2seriesvsparallelcharging"&gt;2. Series vs Parallel charging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Series charging is the conventional method we use which is to charge the battery packs one after another if we have many. But some drone owners are keeping multiple battery packs and are trying to charge them simultaneously using parallel chargers available in the market. Even though I haven’t tried this out by myself from the knowledge I have found in the internet tells &lt;strong&gt;not to use&lt;/strong&gt; parallel charging as it can be really dangerous depending on the variety of batteries connected at the same time and the age of batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="3protectingthechargingsocket"&gt;3. Protecting the charging socket&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the battery packs have a JST- XH connector for the charging connector. When connecting to the charger and removing the wires of the connector can get pulled out or even get short circuit in long run. To solve that balance &lt;strong&gt;protector clips&lt;/strong&gt; are used to cover the charging connector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/06/lipo-battery-balance-lead-protector-clips.jpg" alt="Read this before using lipo batteries again 🔋"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="storinglipobatteries"&gt;Storing lipo batteries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are times where we don’t have time to spend doing our favorite electronic projects and we have to store our battery packs in a way that its health is not affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="1usingfireproofbags"&gt;1. Using fireproof bags&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As lithium ions react with oxygen when exposed to the air, a small puncture in the battery may lead to a fire. Therefore, fireproof bags are used to store the li-po batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/06/lipo-fireproof-bag.png" alt="Read this before using lipo batteries again 🔋"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="2lipostoragecharging"&gt;2. Li-Po storage charging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Li-Po batteries are not advisable to be stored at full discharged stage or fully charged stage. The balanced charger mentioned above has a function called the li-po store mode which charges or discharges each cell to &lt;strong&gt;3.8V&lt;/strong&gt; which is the commonly used voltage to store li-po batteries. It is advised to use this storage mode every time you are stopping using the battery for a couple of days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h2 id="disposinglipobatteries"&gt;Disposing lipo batteries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you have accidently killed your battery or the battery is dead due to aging the batteries should be disposed in a proper way. These are the common steps to be taken to dispose a li-po battery. Please do these steps with caution and have necessary tools with you to face any malfunction of the battery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discharge the li-po battery using the balance charge in a fireproof container&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place the li-po battery terminals in a saltwater for at least 24 hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check to see whether the terminal voltage is 0V. If not go to step 2 again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dispose the battery in the trash as these batteries are not harmful as most of the batteries using different chemistry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a quite lengthy article this marks the end. Here I wanted to share the things I have learned through experience and the internet. If we know all the necessary, stuff about li-po batteries we could save wasted batteries and increase the durability of our batteries while ensuring safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have learned something new from this article, please leave a comment below. If you have any suggestion and improvements to enhance the quality of my articles, please mention below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you. Stay tuned! ❤️&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰</title><description>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Building electronic projects and robotics projects is always fun. There’s no correct way defined strictly as how things are done. We are allowed to use our creative minds to make them unique. Sometimes, using the correct tools for the small tasks in our projects can make our lives easier&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2369/must-have-tools-to-make-your-electronic-projects-easy/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5ea7dbe1e81ef1a07da1dffe</guid><category>Robotics</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 07:41:52 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/electronic-tools-cover.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/electronic-tools-cover.png" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Building electronic projects and robotics projects is always fun. There’s no correct way defined strictly as how things are done. We are allowed to use our creative minds to make them unique. Sometimes, using the correct tools for the small tasks in our projects can make our lives easier and the increase quality of the outcome. Even though we are more used to grab the tools within our reach and build our projects, it’s always good to learn how the things are done correctly with the tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through this article, I would like to share some of the tools I found useful when building my robotics and electronic projects. As some of you might be familiar with all the tools, this article is specially targeted for those who don’t have much idea about the tools as I once were. I will only go through some of the tools I have used. Feel free add your suggestions and comments where I can add them to the post later. Let’s dive into the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the list of tools that was useful to me when building my electronic and robotics projects. It doesn’t mean that all these are needed for every project, but it’s useful to know about the tools anyway!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Gluegun&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/gluegun.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="40%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has made its way to the top of the list is that how this simple tool can help to build your electronic prototypes easily. Reasonable price and the cheaper melting adhesive polymer refills help to stick most of the materials together like wood, acrylic and cardboard. These glue sticks come in different colors to match different applications. Usually the glue is resistant to water, but it cannot withstand high temperature. Even using glue gun is not advisable for professional designs, it always comes handy for prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.	Mini drill set&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/mini_drill.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="40%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us are very familiar with the ordinary hand drill used for drilling holes by the professionals. But for electronic projects we need small drill bits such as 0.8mm, 2mm, 3mm (typically less than 6mm). Therefore, having a mini hand drill will greatly help building our projects. Smaller footprint of mini drill allows less pressure on the drilling point and it’s easier to drill with good accuracy. Some of these have a feature of expanding the shaft using a bendable cable which helps to reach smaller areas. Other than drilling holes many kits come with attachable tools such as cutoff wheels, grinding disks and polishing attachments. Some of the frequent applications I have used in my experience are drilling PCB holes, drilling mounting holes, sharpening tools, cutting off PCBs and cutting acrylic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.	Screwdriver set&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/Screwdriver_set-1.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="40%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tool is the most popular one among the list which I think all of you enthusiasts poses. I wanted to include this just for the sake of making the list complete. I would not dive deep into this tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.	Digital Multimeter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/digital-multimeter.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="40%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I’m basically talking about the portable digital multimeter as it’s cheaper than the higher-grade digital multimeter which can be seen in electronic labs. Some of the basic application in my experiences are,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measuring voltage of power modules and checking logic levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checking resistances of resistors – many through-hole cheap resistors usually don’t come with the accurate resistance values displayed in the color code. It’s always better to measure before using in the project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checking connectivity (diode mode) – when debugging the projects for connectivity issues this feature is a life saver.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measuring current – by measuring the total current consumed by the circuits help to get an idea about the usage time of the device when powered by a battery. I will write a separate article on important things to consider when using li-po batteries in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checking working state of transistors – this is a handy feature of some multimeters to check working condition of BJTs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just the main applications of multimeter. If you have some great features to add please mention below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.	Digital caliper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/vernier_caliper.gif" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="50%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another important tool when taking measurements of components. When we don’t have 3D models of the components, we need to custom design them using the physical dimension measurements. Digital caliper, which is also sometimes incorrectly called as Digital Vernier Caliper can measure internal and external distances with good accuracy rather than using a simple ruler. LCD display is used to display the readings and the locking screw can be used to lock the caliper while taking readings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6.	Plastic cutter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/plastic-cutter.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tool is commonly used in hardware stores to cut large acrylic sheets. The thin blade is so sharp that couple of hard swipes on the plastic surface is enough to break apart the material with torsion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.	Tweezer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/tweezers.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes our 10 fingers are not enough to handle sensitive components and reach small spaces. Tweezers come in handy in this case. I remember removing a wire from the main board of a robot we made. After trying to replace the wire without dissembling the robot with my hands, only after using the tweezers helped me to achieve the task. Tweezers are commonly used in the areas of electronics, craft, jewellery and laboratory work. There different types of tweezers available for different types of uses. Tweezers are usually anti-static, protected from ESD and stainless steel. Main application of tweezers in electronics is the use in soldering SMD components in PCBs. I’m planning to write a separate article of tools for soldering in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8.	Wire cutter (Diagonal plier)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/wire-cutter.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tool is indented to easily cut wires and cables. Having a separate tool with sharpened jaws comes in handy sometimes. This is very popular among electricians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9.	Wire stripper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/wire-striper.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tool helps to remove the insulation of wires for soldering and connecting purposes, which some of are used to do by your teeth. I recommend to use this tool for this application as it’s secure and we can decrease damaging the conducting area of a wire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10.	Wire crimping tool&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/wire-crimper.png" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever wondered how those wires are attached to JST female connectors and jumper wires we often use? Ever wandered to make custom cables for your project. Wire crimping tool comes in handy to make your wire harnessing look professional. This is also a cheap tool to be purchased at the hardware store or from online. This single tool supports connecting of many different kinds of connectors to wires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11.	Angled plier&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/angled-plier.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plier is commonly used to grab components, bending and cutting. Sometimes angled pliers come in handy as they are stronger than tweezers. Therefore, we can grab into components when we want to remove them or do adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12.	Soldering toolkit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/soldering-toolkit.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soldering can be portrayed as another art considering how simple it begins to how complex it can go. Therefore, I’m planning to cover this section in a later post in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13.	Power supply unit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/dc-power-supply-unit.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we need to test our circuits without using battery, we need a reliable power supply unit for testing. I recommend using a good laboratory dc power supply unit even though they are expensive. These power supplies usually come in multiple outputs, output voltage and current control and protection systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think you might have learned something new from the article. It’s fun to work with tools to build our electronics projects. Please mention suggestions to improve my articles in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck in building your next electronic project!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Getting started in the micromouse journey “වේග බට්ටා V1.0” #1 🏎</title><description>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Micromouse is not really like any other robotics competition as I would see. It’s kind of a hobby that someone can master throughout his/her life. Starting from ground up, learning from the basics, there’s long journey to be discovered. All of the great champions in international micromouse&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2369/getting-started-in-the-micromouse-journey-1/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5e9173905c617a076ce34dc1</guid><category>Robotics</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Apr 2020 07:48:12 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/Cover.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/Cover.png" alt="Getting started in the micromouse journey “වේග බට්ටා V1.0” #1 🏎"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Micromouse is not really like any other robotics competition as I would see. It’s kind of a hobby that someone can master throughout his/her life. Starting from ground up, learning from the basics, there’s long journey to be discovered. All of the great champions in international micromouse competitions have started from the very basics. Even though we see the complex robots build by them now, they all have a success story behind them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/GreenYee-s-first-micromouse.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Getting started in the micromouse journey “වේග බට්ටා V1.0” #1 🏎"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;GreenYee's first micrmouse&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first micromouse robot made by “&lt;a href="http://greenye.net/"&gt;GreenYee&lt;/a&gt;” and his team ; the all-time micromouse champion in USA and the founder of &lt;a href="http://micromouseusa.com/"&gt;Micromouse USA&lt;/a&gt; website. It’s not all about doing everything perfect at the first try, but what really matters is the improvement over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;The article series of &lt;strong&gt;“getting started in the micromouse journey”&lt;/strong&gt; is written with the intention of sharing how team &lt;strong&gt;“&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/CircuitBreakersMora/"&gt;CircuitBreakers&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/strong&gt; started its journey of micromouse. In this particular article, I will provide some insight about our first micromouse robot &lt;strong&gt;“වේග බට්ටා V1.0”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started designing our first micromouse robot back in 2018 to participate in the undergraduate level of &lt;strong&gt;“SLIIT Robofest 2018”&lt;/strong&gt;. After we did our initial research on making micromouse, we have realized some basic aspects to be covered initially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding good hardware and build the robot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement and test basic robot functions; turning, moving cells and etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implementing flood fill algorithm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tuning and saving the shortest path&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s move to each aspect in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h1 id="1findinggoodhardwareandbuildtherobot"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1# Finding good hardware and build the robot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here is the list of components we have used to design our robot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pololu 1200rpm HPCB 6V dual shaft micro metal motors x 2&lt;/strong&gt; – These motors are small and easy to control. We had to use custom pwm function to control these motors because they were too fast. For the V2.0 we have used a slower rpm of the same motor for easier control. (&lt;a href="https://www.pololu.com/product/3072"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pololu magnetic encoder pair kit for micro metal gear motors&lt;/strong&gt; – These encoders are a good solution to measure distance travelled by the robot. 12 CPR resolution is reasonable to measure distances accurately. (&lt;a href="https://www.pololu.com/product/3081"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arduino Nano micro controller as the MCU&lt;/strong&gt; – We chose Arduino platform as a good starting point to make a micromouse robot as we were young and inexperienced in this field at the beginning. Considering the smaller form factor we chose Arduino Nano as our solution. (&lt;a href="https://store.arduino.cc/usa/arduino-nano"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dual MC33926 Motor Driver Carrier&lt;/strong&gt; – I had purchased this motor driver previously. Therefore, I used this for the micromouse robot. Any good quality, low power motor controller can be used. But be aware when using low quality L29xx motor controllers as the responsiveness of the robot might be affected by it. (&lt;a href="https://www.pololu.com/product/1213"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MPU6050 Module&lt;/strong&gt; – This is an entry range gyroscope which will suite for types all robotics applications. Other than being very cost effective, this gyro has some very unique features that other higher priced modules lack which I’m planning to cover in another article in the future. (&lt;a href="https://www.electronicwings.com/sensors-modules/mpu6050-gyroscope-accelerometer-temperature-sensor-module"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sharp IR distance sensors&lt;/strong&gt; – These sensors can provide accurate distance measurements even the surface is angled and aren’t affected by the environment, object color or surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a. &lt;strong&gt;4-30cm Distance sensor&lt;/strong&gt; – These sensors were used to measure distance to the walls in front and align the robot correctly before a turn (&lt;a href="https://www.pololu.com/product/2464"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;b. &lt;strong&gt;2-15cm Distance sensor&lt;/strong&gt; – These sensors were used to measure distance to the walls and align the robot parallel to the walls of the maze (&lt;a href="https://www.pololu.com/product/2450"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="7"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5V Buzzer&lt;/strong&gt; – This came in handy as a debugging signal where we used as an auditory feedback for testing the robot. As the Arduino Nano has a smaller memory, we weren’t able to connect an OLED display for visual feedback, therefore using a buzzer was an alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Button Panel&lt;/strong&gt; – This consist of 3 programmable buttons + reset button of the MCU. This button panel has enabled to include several test programs to the robot to check all the basic functions without uploading several programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1200mAh 7.4V lithium ion battery&lt;/strong&gt; – Using 7.4v battery, producing 5v and 6v for the sensors and motors can be easily done using step down convertors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step down convertors&lt;/strong&gt; – Two separate step down convertors were used to provide 5V for the MCU and sensors, 6V for the motor driver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a. &lt;strong&gt;LM2596 Module&lt;/strong&gt; – 6V step down convertor&lt;br&gt;
b. &lt;strong&gt;Mini DC 5v 360 Buck Convetor&lt;/strong&gt; – 5v step down convertor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="11"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HC-05 Bluetooth Module&lt;/strong&gt; – For testing the floodfill algorithm, we have used a Bluetooth module where we can send information to a mobile phone or laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pololu wheels 32x7mm Pair&lt;/strong&gt; - we used these small wheels to suite the small form factor of our robot. smaller wheels give much more control over the speed. (&lt;a href="https://www.pololu.com/product/1088"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have first started with a 10x10cm^2 design and moved to a circular 8x8cm^2 design where we placed motors in the middle of the robot for easier turning of the robot without changing the turning axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/Evolution.PNG" class="kg-image" alt="Getting started in the micromouse journey “වේග බට්ටා V1.0” #1 🏎"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Evolution of micromouse design of “වේග බට්ටා V1.0”&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are a lot to discuss when it comes to the testing and programming a micromouse robot. Therefore, rest of the stages will be discussed in the future articles in this series with the introduction of our next robot &lt;strong&gt;“වේග බට්ටා V2.0”&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;2019&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of our robot performing at the finals of &lt;strong&gt;“SLIIT Robofest 2018”&lt;/strong&gt; competition. Hope you learned something out of my first article in the article series of &lt;strong&gt;“Getting started in the micromouse journey”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always keep in mind to be unique, start slow and grow with time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;iframe width="480" height="270" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lBwDeK8pEL8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;CircuitBreakers at "SLIIT Robofest 2018" finals&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please add your suggestions and questions below to improve my future articles. Good luck making your first micromouse robot. Thank You!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Every day is a chance to learn something new 🤩</title><description>This post is about a newsletter article I wrote to Moratuwa Toastmasters annual newsletter about my journey so far.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/everyday-is-a-chance-to-learn-something-new/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5e05a1b8b0549e59c7054835</guid><category>Lifestyle</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 06:31:40 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/Toastmasters.JPG" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/Toastmasters.JPG" alt="Every day is a chance to learn something new 🤩"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post is based on an article that I wrote to Moratuwa Toastmasters annual newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to introduce myself as a person seeking to learn new things every day. I remember how I would go online to search about new tech stuff and gadgets in my childhood. Let me explain a bit about me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a very studios kid back in my school life where I wanted to do something to make my school and parents proud. I didn't have much choices. Therefore, I chose to study hard to get good grades for A/Ls. As a result, I was able to be among the &lt;strong&gt;top 5 students&lt;/strong&gt; from the country in Physical science stream for GCE A/L exams back in 2016. This achievement changed my life and proved that I'm capable of doing something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After getting selected to Department of Electronic &amp;amp; Telecommunication engineering in the University of Moratuwa I wanted to try myself to see whether I can excel in other areas too hoping to prove the wrong belief &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;studios kids are only good at one thing&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;. I joined AIESEC in 2018 (world's largest youth organization) where I was appointed as the team leader for an energy conservation project named &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;Switch Off 7.0&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot; where we enlightened 4 houses in a rural village providing them electricity through solar panels. Next, I started doing badminton as a sport; humbly saying that I had to learn starting from holding the &amp;quot;racquet&amp;quot; properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You're never too old to start learning, and you're never too young to aim high and achieve great things.&lt;/strong&gt; - Asa Hutchinson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't miss mentioning about my passion for robotics which I accidently figured out with 2 of my friends after competing in a robotic competition. I have participated in more than 8 local robotics competitions in undergraduate level and I was fortunate to achieve victories in most of them. My small team has now grown up to a startup named &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;CircuitBreakers&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;. While trying all these new things, public speaking was one of things I had last in my mind. But, I felt that the effective use of communication skills is the key to share my experience with people. That's the very reason I joined this amazing Moratuwa Toastmasters family where our fear becomes our passion. So far, it has been a great journey with this amazing family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I always believe there's nothing far from our reach. If we put our heart and soul to it, we can definitely achieve our dreams. See every moment as an opportunity to learn something new. At the end you will have so many stories to share with everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>vscode vs jupyter for OpenCV 🚀</title><description>vscode is the most popular coding platform used now. It supports almost all the languages. This is my experiment in replacing jupyter with score.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/vscode-vs-jupyter-for-opencv/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5e049a88d7b20c10ec89b9f5</guid><category>Tech</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 11:34:04 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/vscode-vs-jupyter-2.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/vscode-vs-jupyter-2.png" alt="vscode vs jupyter for OpenCV 🚀"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I always wanted to find effienct and easy tools when I need to do something&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;I recently installed anaconda package for python to learn image processing and machine learning. Most of the people are using jupyter notebook and jupyter lab to open ipython notebooks. ipython notebooks provides the feature to test the code in cell format which helps to easily visualize and debug lengthy code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;As my favourite code editor is &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;vscode&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;, and I use this amazing editor for every coding instance I do right now starting from programming arduinos, STM boards, competitive programming and etc. Therefore, I wanted use vscode for openCV projects too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woolah! ipython notebooks are working in vscode....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;So far, I have only tested this feature in vscode for &lt;strong&gt;macOS&lt;/strong&gt; and it might contain some bugs and few errors. But, it's working fine so far. The best features I have experienced contrasting to jupyter tools are that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;access file menu side by side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use vscode shortcuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;choose python environment from vscode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;support for version control tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vscode extension support and easy searching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a animated gif of using vscode to work with ipython notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-width-wide kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/vscode.gif" class="kg-image" alt="vscode vs jupyter for OpenCV 🚀"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;gif containing a video of using vscode (openCV)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Finding the perfect backpack for university 🎒</title><description>I always wanted a perfect backpack for my university work. After searching so much finally found this amazing backpack.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/finding-the-perfect-smart-backpack/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5e048aeed7b20c10ec89b9dd</guid><category>Lifestyle</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 10:32:02 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/compacto-1.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/compacto-1.jpg" alt="Finding the perfect backpack for university 🎒"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Travelling with a backpack that I don't like is a nightmare to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;I always wanted to find the perfect backpack for my univeristy work, but frustrated of all the options that I could find. Even though the high pricy Swift Gear, Nike, Diesel and ect didn't quite had all the features I have been looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Price is not my concern as even the higher price ones didn't have all the features I'm looking for. I wanted a backpack with many features and custom designed pockets for my favourite items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="herearesomeofthethingsthatihavelookedfor"&gt;Here are some of the things that I have looked for,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;build quility is surely one of the things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to safely store my 13 inch macbook pro, my ipad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to quickly access my power bank and earphones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;store my water bottle in a sealed quickly accessible place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;store my calculator, keys, pens in a separete pockets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;carry clothes or shoes in a separate container where it acts like a luggage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;water and dust proof design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lots of bags were not able to fulfill my expectations and I finally came across this brand called &amp;quot;Mark Ryden&amp;quot; which I wasn't heard before. They have different backpack lineups and type &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;compacto&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot; got my attention. It had almost all the features that I have been looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/backpack.JPG" class="kg-image" alt="Finding the perfect backpack for university 🎒"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;photos taken after receiving the backpack&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;After using the backpack for &lt;strong&gt;more than 8 months&lt;/strong&gt; now, I still enjoying carrying this with me. For all the smart backpack enthusiasts out there I will hope this will help in choosing the perfect backpack for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This backpack costs about 50 usd on aliexpress and the link to product description is below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://markrydenglobal.com/collections/backpacks/products/compacto"&gt;https://markrydenglobal.com/collections/backpacks/products/compacto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following image shows some of the items that this backpack can hold. There are both 15 inch and 17 inch models available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For lighter users, there's another backpack titled as &amp;quot;compacto pro&amp;quot; which is lighter and thinner than &amp;quot;compacto&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/Mark-Ryden-Men-Backpack-Multifunction-USB-Charging-17-Inch-Laptop-Bag-Large-Capacity-Waterproof-Travel-Bags.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Finding the perfect backpack for university 🎒"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;shows the different items that the backpack can store&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Why breadboard testing is essential in robot design? 🔧</title><description>This article might seem strange, but knowing these little things can make your robotics project easier.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/why-breadboard-testing-is-essential-in-robot-design/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5e0450661068980566467972</guid><category>Robotics</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 06:28:03 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/breadbord_testing.JPG" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/breadbord_testing.JPG" alt="Why breadboard testing is essential in robot design? 🔧"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This article might seem strange, but knowing these little things can make your robotics project easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;As making robots have become a part of my university life, I love to design different kinds of robots for local robotics competitions in undergraduate level. Designing a robot can be narrowed down to several steps as follows from my experience,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hardware design stage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breadboard testing stage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PCB designing stage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assembly stage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programming stage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;These stages will mostly overlap between each other and needs to be done parellel in order to succefully finish the project. Most of the people miss the &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;Breadboard testing stage&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot; and directly make the PCB which creates lots of problems like asigning sesors to incompatable pins, wiring issues, wrong selection of components and ect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;This article is about my experience of making a micromouse robot using STMF103C6 &amp;quot;bluepill&amp;quot; board and how properly testing before the final designed helped to build the robot without errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second time I'm making a micrmouse and first time I used an Arduino Nano board to make the robot. The speed of the arduino boards are slow to quickly react to gyro values to accurately navigate and turn in the maze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h4 id="newtostm"&gt;New to STM?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I was new to STM boards I didn't know the correct pins to connect the sensors and to programme it. Therfore before designing a pcb I thought to test everything out using a breadboard.&lt;br&gt;
Following video contains some footage of the breadboard testing stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;iframe width="480" height="270" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lkV5wnVwkrI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Breadnoard testing for making micromouse robot&amp;nbsp;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h4 id="whyshouldyoudoit"&gt;Why should you do it? 💁🏻‍♂️&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have come across situations where that I search through the internet and route the PCB, after testing I findout the pins were assigned wrong. In these situations I have to go through imense work to rewire the pcb externaly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By testing everything in a breadboard helped me to overcome this problem to find out the necessary pins to connect my sensors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>