<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Dee's Blog</title><description>Thoughts, stories and ideas worth sharing.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/</link><image><url>http://localhost:2369/favicon.png</url><title>Dee's Blog</title><link>http://localhost:2369/</link></image><generator>Ghost 3.13</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 17:50:07 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2369/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰</title><description>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Building electronic projects and robotics projects is always fun. There’s no correct way defined strictly as how things are done. We are allowed to use our creative minds to make them unique. Sometimes, using the correct tools for the small tasks in our projects can make our lives easier&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2369/must-have-tools-to-make-your-electronic-projects-easy/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5ea7dbe1e81ef1a07da1dffe</guid><category>Robotics</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 07:41:52 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/electronic-tools-cover.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/electronic-tools-cover.png" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Building electronic projects and robotics projects is always fun. There’s no correct way defined strictly as how things are done. We are allowed to use our creative minds to make them unique. Sometimes, using the correct tools for the small tasks in our projects can make our lives easier and the increase quality of the outcome. Even though we are more used to grab the tools within our reach and build our projects, it’s always good to learn how the things are done correctly with the tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through this article, I would like to share some of the tools I found useful when building my robotics and electronic projects. As some of you might be familiar with all the tools, this article is specially targeted for those who don’t have much idea about the tools as I once were. I will only go through some of the tools I have used. Feel free add your suggestions and comments where I can add them to the post later. Let’s dive into the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the list of tools that was useful to me when building my electronic and robotics projects. It doesn’t mean that all these are needed for every project, but it’s useful to know about the tools anyway!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Gluegun&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/gluegun.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="40%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has made its way to the top of the list is that how this simple tool can help to build your electronic prototypes easily. Reasonable price and the cheaper melting adhesive polymer refills help to stick most of the materials together like wood, acrylic and cardboard. These glue sticks come in different colors to match different applications. Usually the glue is resistant to water, but it cannot withstand high temperature. Even using glue gun is not advisable for professional designs, it always comes handy for prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.	Mini drill set&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/mini_drill.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="40%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us are very familiar with the ordinary hand drill used for drilling holes by the professionals. But for electronic projects we need small drill bits such as 0.8mm, 2mm, 3mm (typically less than 6mm). Therefore, having a mini hand drill will greatly help building our projects. Smaller footprint of mini drill allows less pressure on the drilling point and it’s easier to drill with good accuracy. Some of these have a feature of expanding the shaft using a bendable cable which helps to reach smaller areas. Other than drilling holes many kits come with attachable tools such as cutoff wheels, grinding disks and polishing attachments. Some of the frequent applications I have used in my experience are drilling PCB holes, drilling mounting holes, sharpening tools, cutting off PCBs and cutting acrylic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.	Screwdriver set&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/Screwdriver_set-1.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="40%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tool is the most popular one among the list which I think all of you enthusiasts poses. I wanted to include this just for the sake of making the list complete. I would not dive deep into this tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.	Digital Multimeter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/digital-multimeter.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="40%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I’m basically talking about the portable digital multimeter as it’s cheaper than the higher-grade digital multimeter which can be seen in electronic labs. Some of the basic application in my experiences are,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measuring voltage of power modules and checking logic levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checking resistances of resistors – many through-hole cheap resistors usually don’t come with the accurate resistance values displayed in the color code. It’s always better to measure before using in the project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checking connectivity (diode mode) – when debugging the projects for connectivity issues this feature is a life saver.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Measuring current – by measuring the total current consumed by the circuits help to get an idea about the usage time of the device when powered by a battery. I will write a separate article on important things to consider when using li-po batteries in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checking working state of transistors – this is a handy feature of some multimeters to check working condition of BJTs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just the main applications of multimeter. If you have some great features to add please mention below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.	Digital caliper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/vernier_caliper.gif" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="50%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another important tool when taking measurements of components. When we don’t have 3D models of the components, we need to custom design them using the physical dimension measurements. Digital caliper, which is also sometimes incorrectly called as Digital Vernier Caliper can measure internal and external distances with good accuracy rather than using a simple ruler. LCD display is used to display the readings and the locking screw can be used to lock the caliper while taking readings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6.	Plastic cutter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/plastic-cutter.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tool is commonly used in hardware stores to cut large acrylic sheets. The thin blade is so sharp that couple of hard swipes on the plastic surface is enough to break apart the material with torsion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.	Tweezer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/tweezers.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes our 10 fingers are not enough to handle sensitive components and reach small spaces. Tweezers come in handy in this case. I remember removing a wire from the main board of a robot we made. After trying to replace the wire without dissembling the robot with my hands, only after using the tweezers helped me to achieve the task. Tweezers are commonly used in the areas of electronics, craft, jewellery and laboratory work. There different types of tweezers available for different types of uses. Tweezers are usually anti-static, protected from ESD and stainless steel. Main application of tweezers in electronics is the use in soldering SMD components in PCBs. I’m planning to write a separate article of tools for soldering in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8.	Wire cutter (Diagonal plier)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/wire-cutter.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tool is indented to easily cut wires and cables. Having a separate tool with sharpened jaws comes in handy sometimes. This is very popular among electricians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9.	Wire stripper&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/wire-striper.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tool helps to remove the insulation of wires for soldering and connecting purposes, which some of are used to do by your teeth. I recommend to use this tool for this application as it’s secure and we can decrease damaging the conducting area of a wire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10.	Wire crimping tool&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/wire-crimper.png" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever wondered how those wires are attached to JST female connectors and jumper wires we often use? Ever wandered to make custom cables for your project. Wire crimping tool comes in handy to make your wire harnessing look professional. This is also a cheap tool to be purchased at the hardware store or from online. This single tool supports connecting of many different kinds of connectors to wires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11.	Angled plier&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/angled-plier.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plier is commonly used to grab components, bending and cutting. Sometimes angled pliers come in handy as they are stronger than tweezers. Therefore, we can grab into components when we want to remove them or do adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12.	Soldering toolkit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/soldering-toolkit.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soldering can be portrayed as another art considering how simple it begins to how complex it can go. Therefore, I’m planning to cover this section in a later post in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13.	Power supply unit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/dc-power-supply-unit.jpg" alt="Must have tools to make your electronic projects easy 🧰" style="float:right; margin:1em;" width="30%"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we need to test our circuits without using battery, we need a reliable power supply unit for testing. I recommend using a good laboratory dc power supply unit even though they are expensive. These power supplies usually come in multiple outputs, output voltage and current control and protection systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think you might have learned something new from the article. It’s fun to work with tools to build our electronics projects. Please mention suggestions to improve my articles in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck in building your next electronic project!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Getting started in the micromouse journey “වේග බට්ටා V1.0” #1 🏎</title><description>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Micromouse is not really like any other robotics competition as I would see. It’s kind of a hobby that someone can master throughout his/her life. Starting from ground up, learning from the basics, there’s long journey to be discovered. All of the great champions in international micromouse&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2369/getting-started-in-the-micromouse-journey-1/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5e9173905c617a076ce34dc1</guid><category>Robotics</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Apr 2020 07:48:12 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/Cover.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/Cover.png" alt="Getting started in the micromouse journey “වේග බට්ටා V1.0” #1 🏎"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Micromouse is not really like any other robotics competition as I would see. It’s kind of a hobby that someone can master throughout his/her life. Starting from ground up, learning from the basics, there’s long journey to be discovered. All of the great champions in international micromouse competitions have started from the very basics. Even though we see the complex robots build by them now, they all have a success story behind them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/GreenYee-s-first-micromouse.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Getting started in the micromouse journey “වේග බට්ටා V1.0” #1 🏎"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;GreenYee's first micrmouse&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first micromouse robot made by “&lt;a href="http://greenye.net/"&gt;GreenYee&lt;/a&gt;” and his team ; the all-time micromouse champion in USA and the founder of &lt;a href="http://micromouseusa.com/"&gt;Micromouse USA&lt;/a&gt; website. It’s not all about doing everything perfect at the first try, but what really matters is the improvement over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;The article series of &lt;strong&gt;“getting started in the micromouse journey”&lt;/strong&gt; is written with the intention of sharing how team &lt;strong&gt;“&lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/CircuitBreakersMora/"&gt;CircuitBreakers&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/strong&gt; started its journey of micromouse. In this particular article, I will provide some insight about our first micromouse robot &lt;strong&gt;“වේග බට්ටා V1.0”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started designing our first micromouse robot back in 2018 to participate in the undergraduate level of &lt;strong&gt;“SLIIT Robofest 2018”&lt;/strong&gt;. After we did our initial research on making micromouse, we have realized some basic aspects to be covered initially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finding good hardware and build the robot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement and test basic robot functions; turning, moving cells and etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implementing flood fill algorithm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tuning and saving the shortest path&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s move to each aspect in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h1 id="1findinggoodhardwareandbuildtherobot"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1# Finding good hardware and build the robot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here is the list of components we have used to design our robot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pololu 1200rpm HPCB 6V dual shaft micro metal motors x 2&lt;/strong&gt; – These motors are small and easy to control. We had to use custom pwm function to control these motors because they were too fast. For the V2.0 we have used a slower rpm of the same motor for easier control. (&lt;a href="https://www.pololu.com/product/3072"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pololu magnetic encoder pair kit for micro metal gear motors&lt;/strong&gt; – These encoders are a good solution to measure distance travelled by the robot. 12 CPR resolution is reasonable to measure distances accurately. (&lt;a href="https://www.pololu.com/product/3081"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arduino Nano micro controller as the MCU&lt;/strong&gt; – We chose Arduino platform as a good starting point to make a micromouse robot as we were young and inexperienced in this field at the beginning. Considering the smaller form factor we chose Arduino Nano as our solution. (&lt;a href="https://store.arduino.cc/usa/arduino-nano"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dual MC33926 Motor Driver Carrier&lt;/strong&gt; – I had purchased this motor driver previously. Therefore, I used this for the micromouse robot. Any good quality, low power motor controller can be used. But be aware when using low quality L29xx motor controllers as the responsiveness of the robot might be affected by it. (&lt;a href="https://www.pololu.com/product/1213"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MPU6050 Module&lt;/strong&gt; – This is an entry range gyroscope which will suite for types all robotics applications. Other than being very cost effective, this gyro has some very unique features that other higher priced modules lack which I’m planning to cover in another article in the future. (&lt;a href="https://www.electronicwings.com/sensors-modules/mpu6050-gyroscope-accelerometer-temperature-sensor-module"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sharp IR distance sensors&lt;/strong&gt; – These sensors can provide accurate distance measurements even the surface is angled and aren’t affected by the environment, object color or surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a. &lt;strong&gt;4-30cm Distance sensor&lt;/strong&gt; – These sensors were used to measure distance to the walls in front and align the robot correctly before a turn (&lt;a href="https://www.pololu.com/product/2464"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;b. &lt;strong&gt;2-15cm Distance sensor&lt;/strong&gt; – These sensors were used to measure distance to the walls and align the robot parallel to the walls of the maze (&lt;a href="https://www.pololu.com/product/2450"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="7"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5V Buzzer&lt;/strong&gt; – This came in handy as a debugging signal where we used as an auditory feedback for testing the robot. As the Arduino Nano has a smaller memory, we weren’t able to connect an OLED display for visual feedback, therefore using a buzzer was an alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Button Panel&lt;/strong&gt; – This consist of 3 programmable buttons + reset button of the MCU. This button panel has enabled to include several test programs to the robot to check all the basic functions without uploading several programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1200mAh 7.4V lithium ion battery&lt;/strong&gt; – Using 7.4v battery, producing 5v and 6v for the sensors and motors can be easily done using step down convertors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step down convertors&lt;/strong&gt; – Two separate step down convertors were used to provide 5V for the MCU and sensors, 6V for the motor driver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a. &lt;strong&gt;LM2596 Module&lt;/strong&gt; – 6V step down convertor&lt;br&gt;
b. &lt;strong&gt;Mini DC 5v 360 Buck Convetor&lt;/strong&gt; – 5v step down convertor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="11"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HC-05 Bluetooth Module&lt;/strong&gt; – For testing the floodfill algorithm, we have used a Bluetooth module where we can send information to a mobile phone or laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pololu wheels 32x7mm Pair&lt;/strong&gt; - we used these small wheels to suite the small form factor of our robot. smaller wheels give much more control over the speed. (&lt;a href="https://www.pololu.com/product/1088"&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have first started with a 10x10cm^2 design and moved to a circular 8x8cm^2 design where we placed motors in the middle of the robot for easier turning of the robot without changing the turning axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2020/04/Evolution.PNG" class="kg-image" alt="Getting started in the micromouse journey “වේග බට්ටා V1.0” #1 🏎"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Evolution of micromouse design of “වේග බට්ටා V1.0”&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are a lot to discuss when it comes to the testing and programming a micromouse robot. Therefore, rest of the stages will be discussed in the future articles in this series with the introduction of our next robot &lt;strong&gt;“වේග බට්ටා V2.0”&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;2019&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video of our robot performing at the finals of &lt;strong&gt;“SLIIT Robofest 2018”&lt;/strong&gt; competition. Hope you learned something out of my first article in the article series of &lt;strong&gt;“Getting started in the micromouse journey”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always keep in mind to be unique, start slow and grow with time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;iframe width="480" height="270" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lBwDeK8pEL8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;CircuitBreakers at "SLIIT Robofest 2018" finals&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please add your suggestions and questions below to improve my future articles. Good luck making your first micromouse robot. Thank You!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Every day is a chance to learn something new 🤩</title><description>This post is about a newsletter article I wrote to Moratuwa Toastmasters annual newsletter about my journey so far.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/everyday-is-a-chance-to-learn-something-new/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5e05a1b8b0549e59c7054835</guid><category>Lifestyle</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 06:31:40 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/Toastmasters.JPG" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/Toastmasters.JPG" alt="Every day is a chance to learn something new 🤩"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post is based on an article that I wrote to Moratuwa Toastmasters annual newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would like to introduce myself as a person seeking to learn new things every day. I remember how I would go online to search about new tech stuff and gadgets in my childhood. Let me explain a bit about me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a very studios kid back in my school life where I wanted to do something to make my school and parents proud. I didn't have much choices. Therefore, I chose to study hard to get good grades for A/Ls. As a result, I was able to be among the &lt;strong&gt;top 5 students&lt;/strong&gt; from the country in Physical science stream for GCE A/L exams back in 2016. This achievement changed my life and proved that I'm capable of doing something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After getting selected to Department of Electronic &amp;amp; Telecommunication engineering in the University of Moratuwa I wanted to try myself to see whether I can excel in other areas too hoping to prove the wrong belief &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;studios kids are only good at one thing&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;. I joined AIESEC in 2018 (world's largest youth organization) where I was appointed as the team leader for an energy conservation project named &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;Switch Off 7.0&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot; where we enlightened 4 houses in a rural village providing them electricity through solar panels. Next, I started doing badminton as a sport; humbly saying that I had to learn starting from holding the &amp;quot;racquet&amp;quot; properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You're never too old to start learning, and you're never too young to aim high and achieve great things.&lt;/strong&gt; - Asa Hutchinson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't miss mentioning about my passion for robotics which I accidently figured out with 2 of my friends after competing in a robotic competition. I have participated in more than 8 local robotics competitions in undergraduate level and I was fortunate to achieve victories in most of them. My small team has now grown up to a startup named &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;CircuitBreakers&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;. While trying all these new things, public speaking was one of things I had last in my mind. But, I felt that the effective use of communication skills is the key to share my experience with people. That's the very reason I joined this amazing Moratuwa Toastmasters family where our fear becomes our passion. So far, it has been a great journey with this amazing family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I always believe there's nothing far from our reach. If we put our heart and soul to it, we can definitely achieve our dreams. See every moment as an opportunity to learn something new. At the end you will have so many stories to share with everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>vscode vs jupyter for OpenCV 🚀</title><description>vscode is the most popular coding platform used now. It supports almost all the languages. This is my experiment in replacing jupyter with score.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/vscode-vs-jupyter-for-opencv/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5e049a88d7b20c10ec89b9f5</guid><category>Tech</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 11:34:04 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/vscode-vs-jupyter-2.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/vscode-vs-jupyter-2.png" alt="vscode vs jupyter for OpenCV 🚀"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I always wanted to find effienct and easy tools when I need to do something&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;I recently installed anaconda package for python to learn image processing and machine learning. Most of the people are using jupyter notebook and jupyter lab to open ipython notebooks. ipython notebooks provides the feature to test the code in cell format which helps to easily visualize and debug lengthy code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;As my favourite code editor is &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;vscode&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot;, and I use this amazing editor for every coding instance I do right now starting from programming arduinos, STM boards, competitive programming and etc. Therefore, I wanted use vscode for openCV projects too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woolah! ipython notebooks are working in vscode....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;So far, I have only tested this feature in vscode for &lt;strong&gt;macOS&lt;/strong&gt; and it might contain some bugs and few errors. But, it's working fine so far. The best features I have experienced contrasting to jupyter tools are that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;access file menu side by side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use vscode shortcuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;choose python environment from vscode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;support for version control tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vscode extension support and easy searching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a animated gif of using vscode to work with ipython notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-width-wide kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/vscode.gif" class="kg-image" alt="vscode vs jupyter for OpenCV 🚀"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;gif containing a video of using vscode (openCV)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Finding the perfect backpack for university 🎒</title><description>I always wanted a perfect backpack for my university work. After searching so much finally found this amazing backpack.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/finding-the-perfect-smart-backpack/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5e048aeed7b20c10ec89b9dd</guid><category>Lifestyle</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 10:32:02 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/compacto-1.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/compacto-1.jpg" alt="Finding the perfect backpack for university 🎒"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Travelling with a backpack that I don't like is a nightmare to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;I always wanted to find the perfect backpack for my univeristy work, but frustrated of all the options that I could find. Even though the high pricy Swift Gear, Nike, Diesel and ect didn't quite had all the features I have been looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Price is not my concern as even the higher price ones didn't have all the features I'm looking for. I wanted a backpack with many features and custom designed pockets for my favourite items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="herearesomeofthethingsthatihavelookedfor"&gt;Here are some of the things that I have looked for,&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;build quility is surely one of the things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to safely store my 13 inch macbook pro, my ipad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to quickly access my power bank and earphones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;store my water bottle in a sealed quickly accessible place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;store my calculator, keys, pens in a separete pockets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;carry clothes or shoes in a separate container where it acts like a luggage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;water and dust proof design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lots of bags were not able to fulfill my expectations and I finally came across this brand called &amp;quot;Mark Ryden&amp;quot; which I wasn't heard before. They have different backpack lineups and type &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;compacto&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot; got my attention. It had almost all the features that I have been looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/backpack.JPG" class="kg-image" alt="Finding the perfect backpack for university 🎒"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;photos taken after receiving the backpack&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;After using the backpack for &lt;strong&gt;more than 8 months&lt;/strong&gt; now, I still enjoying carrying this with me. For all the smart backpack enthusiasts out there I will hope this will help in choosing the perfect backpack for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This backpack costs about 50 usd on aliexpress and the link to product description is below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://markrydenglobal.com/collections/backpacks/products/compacto"&gt;https://markrydenglobal.com/collections/backpacks/products/compacto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following image shows some of the items that this backpack can hold. There are both 15 inch and 17 inch models available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For lighter users, there's another backpack titled as &amp;quot;compacto pro&amp;quot; which is lighter and thinner than &amp;quot;compacto&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/Mark-Ryden-Men-Backpack-Multifunction-USB-Charging-17-Inch-Laptop-Bag-Large-Capacity-Waterproof-Travel-Bags.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Finding the perfect backpack for university 🎒"&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;shows the different items that the backpack can store&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Why breadboard testing is essential in robot design? 🔧</title><description>This article might seem strange, but knowing these little things can make your robotics project easier.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/why-breadboard-testing-is-essential-in-robot-design/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5e0450661068980566467972</guid><category>Robotics</category><dc:creator>Deepana Ishtaweera</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 06:28:03 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/breadbord_testing.JPG" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2019/12/breadbord_testing.JPG" alt="Why breadboard testing is essential in robot design? 🔧"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This article might seem strange, but knowing these little things can make your robotics project easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;As making robots have become a part of my university life, I love to design different kinds of robots for local robotics competitions in undergraduate level. Designing a robot can be narrowed down to several steps as follows from my experience,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hardware design stage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breadboard testing stage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PCB designing stage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assembly stage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programming stage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;These stages will mostly overlap between each other and needs to be done parellel in order to succefully finish the project. Most of the people miss the &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;Breadboard testing stage&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot; and directly make the PCB which creates lots of problems like asigning sesors to incompatable pins, wiring issues, wrong selection of components and ect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;This article is about my experience of making a micromouse robot using STMF103C6 &amp;quot;bluepill&amp;quot; board and how properly testing before the final designed helped to build the robot without errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second time I'm making a micrmouse and first time I used an Arduino Nano board to make the robot. The speed of the arduino boards are slow to quickly react to gyro values to accurately navigate and turn in the maze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h4 id="newtostm"&gt;New to STM?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I was new to STM boards I didn't know the correct pins to connect the sensors and to programme it. Therfore before designing a pcb I thought to test everything out using a breadboard.&lt;br&gt;
Following video contains some footage of the breadboard testing stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card kg-card-hascaption"&gt;&lt;iframe width="480" height="270" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lkV5wnVwkrI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Breadnoard testing for making micromouse robot&amp;nbsp;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--kg-card-begin: markdown--&gt;&lt;h4 id="whyshouldyoudoit"&gt;Why should you do it? 💁🏻‍♂️&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have come across situations where that I search through the internet and route the PCB, after testing I findout the pins were assigned wrong. In these situations I have to go through imense work to rewire the pcb externaly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By testing everything in a breadboard helped me to overcome this problem to find out the necessary pins to connect my sensors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--kg-card-end: markdown--&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>